Guide to the Barney Lee Jones Papers, 1957-1995
Duke University. University Archives
Barney Lee Jones papers 1957-1995
Duke University. University Archives
Jones, Barney Lee
1.5 linear feet Extent: 1000 Items
Barney Lee Jones was born in Raleigh, NC on June 11, 1920, the only child of Barney Lee Jones and Gladys Estelle Upshur. He worked as an instructor in the Department of Religion from 1948-1950. In 1953, Barney returned to Duke for the rest of his professional career. He served as Chaplain to the University until 1956 when he moved into the administration and instructional arenas as Assistant Dean of Trinity College and Assistant Professor in the Department of Religion. He received his PhD from the Divinity School in 1958. The collection contains materials donated by Dr. Barney Jones, including his memories of Duke from 1930-1960, correspondence, material from the Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences meetings, and clippings. The material ranges in dates from 1957-1995.
UA.29.02.0087
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
Collection is open for research.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Barney Lee Jones Papers were received by the University Archives as a gift in 1973-1995.
Biographical Note
Barney Lee Jones was born in Raleigh, NC on June 11, 1920, the only child of Barney Lee Jones and Gladys Estelle Upshur. Orphaned at an early age, he was raised in Norfolk, VA by his aunt, Mary Lee Upshur and her husband Roy Elliott. He was greatly influenced by his grandmothers: Julia Estelle (Stella) Andrews Upshur, a Norfolk newspaperwoman, urged him to take his studies seriously; Hattie Parker Jones nurtured his faith during his summers on the family farm in North Carolina.
After graduating from Maury High School in Norfolk in 1938, Barney attended Duke University where he received his BA in 1941. While enrolled at Yale University Divinity School, he served as pastor of the United Methodist Church of Woodbury, CT. He also met fellow student Marjorie H. Curts, whom he married on June 5, 1944. Upon completing his Bachelor of Divinity degree, Jones enlisted as a chaplain in the US Navy (1944-1946) and served in the Pacific theater during the last months of World War II. He returned to the Navy to serve in the Korean War after doing graduate work at Yale (1946-1948) and working as an instructor in the Department of Religion at Duke (1948-1950).
In 1953, Barney returned to Duke for the rest of his professional career. He served as Chaplain to the University until 1956 when he moved into the administration and instructional arenas as Assistant Dean of Trinity College and Assistant Professor in the Department of Religion. He received his PhD from the Divinity School in 1958. Dr. Jones received the Duke Alumni Association's "Distinguished Undergraduate Teaching Award" for the 1977-1978 academic year. He retired from Duke University as Professor Emeritus in 1984. He died from cancer on April 12, 2005 at his home in New York.
Collection Overview
Contains materials donated by Dr. Barney Jones, including his memories of Duke from 1930-1960, correspondence, material from the Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences meetings, and clippings. The material ranges in dates from 1957-1995.
Subject Headings
Manchester, Alan Krebs, b. 1897; Gross, Paul Magnus, 1895-1986; Edens, Arthur Hollis, 1901-; Cleland, James T. (James Tough), 1903-; Duke University -- History -- 20th century; Duke University. School of Religion; Student activism; Reminiscing
Related Material
News Service Biographical Files, 1960-2004,
Duke University Archives
Biographical Reference Collection, 1972-2004
Duke University Archives
Paul M. Gross Papers, 1939-1979
Duke University Archives
A. Hollis Edens Records, 1949-1960
Duke University Archives
James T. Cleland Papers, 1928-1975
Duke University Archives
Alan K. Manchester Papers, 1905-1975
Duke University Archives
Trinity College of Arts and Sciences, Office of the Dean Records, 1948-2003
Duke University Archives
Contents of Collection
- Container List
  - Correspondence, 1968-1970, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Alcohol Problem at Duke, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Chapel Reminiscences: The First Two Decades. Friends of the Chapel Annual Dinner, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Convocation Addresses, 1982 August 27 (Box 1)
  - Ubukata Letter, International Christian University, Japan, 1958 (Box 1)
  - Jones-Womble on Educational Philosophy at Duke, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Fallout Preparedness, 1961-1964 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum, Long-range planning, 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Once-Place Decimal Table of Quality, Point Rations, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Report on Joe College Weekend, 1959 (Box 1)
  - Reorganization of Trinity College and Woman's College, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Remarks to Trinity College Graduates, Commencement, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Reminiscences, 1930-1960, 1975 (Box 1)
  - Convocation Address to Faculty at Marietta College, 1981 August 21 (Box 2)
  - Duke University Chapel brochure, 1966 (Box 2)
  - James T. Cleland, 1970-1980 (Box 2)
  - Duke University Church, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Eulogies, Memorial Services, 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Becky Heron, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Letter from Dr. Jones to Dr. Cleland re: Edens-Gross Affair, 1960 June 17 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence and Reports between Drs. Jones and Alan Manchester, 1958-1964 (Box 2)
  - Theodore W. Minah, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Hiram Earl Myers Memorial, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Physical Education at Duke, 1963 (Box 2)
  - Religion 50.4, 1980 February 27 (Box 2)
  - Department of Religion Meeting, 1980 February 22 (Box 2)
  - Institutional Self-Study, Department of Religion, 1965 (Box 2)
  - Social Regulations, Residential, 1971 (Box 2)
  - Duke University Chapel, 1979-1983 (Box 2)
  - Educational Philosophy at Duke University, 1962 (Box 2)
  - Duke Chapel 50th Anniversary Committee, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Student Activism, Vigil, Allen Building Takeover, 1967-1970 (Box 2)
  - Dean of the Chapel, 1961-1975 (Box 2)
  - Hiram Earl Myers, 1970, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - Undergraduate Faculty Council of Arts and Sciences (UFCAS), 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - UFCAS, Wardropper Report, 1980 (Box 3)
  - UFCAS, 1974 (Box 3)